DAVID J. MALAN: But why don't we
begin now with internet technology.
The goal of the session
being to better understand
how this thing works that most of us
use every day, how we can leverage it,
and most importantly, try to build
it conceptually from the ground up.
So that after today
and after tomorrow, you
have not only the practical benefit
of being able to diagnose things
in the real world a
little more effectively,
you've sort of had the
opportunity to think through,
with the proverbial engineering hat,
how you could go about building things.
That at first glance might
seem so terribly complex,
but at the end of the day
are the result of some fairly
logical well-defined decisions,
again layering from bottom to top.
So with that said, what is the internet?
Let's start there.
Half of you are on it right now, so
you must know what is the internet?
What is the internet?
Yes.
Sean.
AUDIENCE: It's a way to access different
websites, I guess, [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So a way to access different
websites, network structure.
OK.
Let's dive in a little more physically.
So that's what it does.
What is it actually?
What do you got, [? Abi ?]?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Good.
More precise.
So a network of devices.
And a network is just an
interconnection of things.
And those devices, we'll just
simplify, in their computers--
though very much in vogue these
days is IOT or internet of things.
Which means like every stupid
little thing in the world
is going to be on the
internet for some reason.
So that's trendy right now.
But for today we'll just
focus on devices or computers.
And what does it mean to network them.
Well, back in the day it meant
physically connecting them with cables,
so that you could actually have a
physical connection between devices.
Nowadays, we, of course,
have these antennas
on the wall called access
points, or Wi-Fi routers,
or any number of other names for them.
But that allows us to all
transmit data wirelessly.
So that might give us locally what
we call a local area network or LAN.
People don't say that as
much anymore but that's
what a local area network is.
You also have WLAN, which is a wireless
local area network, which probably
even fewer people say these days.
But these are indeed local networks.
So what is the internet?
Well, the internet is really
just a network of networks.
So we might think of this campus,
of course, as being Harvard.edu.
Down the road is MIT.edu.
Across the country is stanford.edu.
Not to mention all of the many
companies and universities and homes
that are out there.
And so all of those, if
they're interconnected,
indeed give us the
internet or inter-network.
All right.
So how does it work?
So I've just walked into
this room a little bit ago.
I open my laptop screen.
And somehow I'm magically
on the internet.
I'm connected to the internet.
But a few steps had to precede that.
Some of you engaged in those steps while
you were here on campus this weekend,
or first thing this morning by
following some of the instructions.
What was one of the first
things you had to do
according to the instructions
in this booklet today?
You had to connect and log on.
So most of you probably have the
intuitive-- the instincts these days,
when you want to connect on
Wi-Fi, you go to your Wi-Fi menu
in the top right or bottom
right corner of your screen,
whatever operating system you're using.
And you choose either the most
familiar or the most unlocked network
that you possibly can
and try to get online.
Sometimes you're asked for a password.
Sometimes you aren't.
And that may or may not have
some actual implications
that we'll perhaps scratch
the surface of today.
Or talk about in more detail
tomorrow morning with security.
But what then happened thereafter?
Well, it turns out that every computer
on the internet has a unique address.
A unique IP address.
I'll just toss up jargon here as
we discuss some of these things.
IP stands for internet protocol.
And it's just a convention for
assigning numeric addresses
to most every computer on the internet.
So we right now are at One Brattle
Square in Cambridge, Massachusetts,
01238.
But that pretty much
uniquely identifies us.
Especially if we tack on the room
number or the floor number and so forth.
And so that's how the
mail-- the post office
actually gets mail uniquely to
this particular destination.
So my laptop too isn't addressed, of
course, by nature of postal addresses,
but by way of numeric addresses.
Just because computers kind
of prefer numeric addresses.
Turns out, fun fact, that these
are 32-bit addresses mostly.
And that means we can have how many
total computers on the internet?
2 to the 32.
Nice way to punt there.
Four billion roughly.
So 2 to the 32 or four billion.
Which actually these
days isn't all that many,
if you consider all of
the humans in the world,
and all of the laptops
and desktops and phones.
And again, because of internet of
things, every toaster and thermostats.
And any number of other devices.
So the world has been transitioning
away from something called IPv4, which
is version 4, the version we've been
using for decades right now, to IPv6.
Which has been around for
a while, but no one really
got around to implementing
it until really recent years.
At least on any kind of scale, with
big companies like Google and Comcast
and the like finally starting to give
people not just 32-bit addresses,
but-- anyone want to take a guess
what comes after 64-- uh, dammit.
What comes after 32-bit addresses?
No.
128-bit addresses, actually.
So I don't even know why I said that.
128-bit addresses.
Which is kind of unprecedented.
Rarely do humans actually
have the foresight
to not just go one notch above but two
notches above where we currently are.
And so 128-bit addresses means that we
really can have an internet of things.
If I pull up my massive calculator here.
2 to the 32, of course, gives
us four billion computers.
2 to the 128, also
unpronounceable by me.
That's a lot of devices.
That's a lot of things on the internet.
So we've got a lot of
IP addresses available,
at least in the works right now.
So what does it mean
to have an IP address?
Well, once my computer
has an IP address--
and how it gets that
we'll come back to-- I
can now communicate on the network.
And indeed the way devices
on the network work
is essentially you
can think of computers
as sending envelopes of information.
So here's like an old
school envelope here.
And on this in the human
world we might typically
put a to address and a from address.
And those would be
physical postal addresses.
But in the digital
world, of course, it's
going to be a numeric address, in
both the to field and the from field.
Which is to say that both I and
the recipient of any information I
send on the internet has got
to have such a numeric address.
So Amazon has such an address,
Google has such an address.
And actually those
bigger fish in the world
tend to often have
multiple IP addresses.
And we can see this.
So first on Mac OS, let me go to
System Preferences and Network.
And Windows has an analog as well.
I'm going to click Advanced, and
I'm going to click on TCP/IP.
And indeed, you can see that my
computer has currently the IP address
10.254.16.128 and a whole
bunch of other things.
So that is the unique address
for my computer right now.
And I should really say unique address.
Because it turns out that
even though much of the world
still uses IPv4 or 32-bit
addresses, the world also
has started using a technology
for some time now called NAT.
Does anyone use this technology at home?
David?
I do.
This is one of those trick questions.
Like who has internet at home?
OK so with very-- and how many
people have Wi-Fi at home?
Almost everyone?
OK.
So with very, very high probability,
all of us in this room use NAT.
NAT is network address translation.
And what this means is that
whether your ISP-- internet service
provider-- is Comcast or RCN or Verizon
or any number of other companies,
probably when they
installed it in your house
they gave you some
kind of little device.
A little router as it might be called.
Although they have different names.
Sometimes they're wireless,
sometimes they're wired.
But connected to that is probably a
telephone line or a coaxial cable,
like your cable box and so forth.
And that is what gives
your house internet access.
And that device comes with
typically one IP address.
And that IP address is
associated with that machine.
The problem, of course, is that most of
us have a phone and a laptop or desktop
or roommates or parents or
siblings or kids, all of whom
themselves have devices.
And so it would be
unfortunate if you only
had one unique address for
all of you if only one of you
could therefore be on
the internet at a time.
NAT came about-- network
address translation--
because it's a feature
of modern hardware
that allows you to have
one IP address for that one
device, the router you bought or
leased from Comcast or the like.
But behind that device,
your home network-- a.k.a.
LAN-- you can have
all dozens of devices,
if not hundreds of devices,
all having not that public IP
address, but private IP addresses.
And so network address translation
essentially works like this.
If this here is your home, and you have
a little box from Verizon or Comcast.
And this here is the internet.
This device here is your home router.
And it has a public IP on this side.
And inside the house are let's
say many private IP addresses.
One for each of the
devices in your homes.
And so any time you send a request from
your laptop for CNN.com or Google.com
or Facebook.com or the like,
that request initially,
by nature of the wires or Wi-Fi in your
house, first go through that device.
Because it's the only point
coming in or going out
to your internet service provider.
It looks at your from address, which
is going to be a private address.
Which just means it's not meant
to be public on the internet.
It quickly crosses that out.
This device puts its
own public IP address
that you get from Comcast or
Verizon where the from field
used to be on that envelope.
Sends it out on the internet.
Google or Facebook or whoever respond.
That response comes to that
little device in your home.
Your little device in your
home checks its records.
Saying hm, who requested this piece
of information a split second ago?
It crosses out the to field,
which was sent to the public IP.
Puts in the private address of
the laptop or desktop or phone
in your home that
originally requested it.
And all of this happens
nearly instantaneously.
So we don't even notice the difference.
But as a result of this network
address translation from public IP
to private IP addresses,
plural, do we have the ability
to put multiple devices
on the network at once.
It wasn't all that long
ago, 20 or so years ago,
when if you wanted to have two
computers on the network at home,
someone like Comcast or RCN would
just charge you twice or three times
to actually give you dedicated
devices or IP addresses.
So this is actually a wonderful feature.
And it has the side effect also
of firewalling your computer.
And this is why these terms
get so commingled these days.
A firewall in the real world is
like a physical wall between stores,
especially in strip malls and the like.
So that if one shop gets on
fire, the other's next to it
with high probability are safe.
Because the fire can't
get through the firewall.
In the virtual world,
you have firewalls that
are software, that are
designed to keep data
from the outside coming in or
perhaps from the inside going out.
And so the fact that there is this
translation from public to private
also means as a side effect,
typically, that if you
have some adversary, some bad
guy on the internet trying
to get at your laptop or desktop in your
home, he or she can't actually do that.
Because the only way you
can talk to a private IP
address is if the request were
initiated from the inside out.
Now, you can firewall your home and your
business even more securely than that.
And we'll come back to that
as we discuss security itself.
And there are ways around the
scenario I just described.
But that tends to be a side effect.
It's a good thing, actually, there's
this network address translation.
Because it means people can't very
easily get in from the outside.
The downside of that is that if
you're trying to run your own web
server-- for instance, you're
trying to start a company
or you're building a website, and you
want friends or associates or just
customers to be able to access your
website and it's inside your home,
odds are they're not
going to be able to.
Because you can't talk
to a private IP address
from the outside world in unless
you configure your home network
or your office network
especially for that.
So there's some interesting layers
of protection that are in here.
Also on the screen here are
a couple of other addresses.
So router.
Let's come here.
I just drew the internet
as this big cloud.
Sort of which has become
cloud computing these days.
But what is the internet itself?
Or what really gets data
from point A to point B?
If this is me at home,
and this is Amazon.com,
how do I actually get data
to and from Amazon.com?
Well, I certainly don't have a Wi-Fi
connection to Amazon in Seattle
or wherever they are.
I certainly don't have a dedicated
wire from my laptop to Amazon.
So once the data leaves
my laptop, where does it
go if I'm trying to shop on Amazon.com?
To a cable?
OK.
So some cable somewhere.
Indeed.
And my laptop probably
is talking wireless
to some of these antennas in the room.
Those antennas-- even
though you don't see them,
because they've been mounted
pretty cleanly on the wall--
do have an ethernet cable that
is quite like this thing here.
It's like a thicker phone cable, if you
remember what phone cables are like.
This is an RJ45 connector.
Phone cables are RJ11, which
just means their size and specs.
But that thing in the wall
is somehow connected probably
to a device called a switch.
So that thing is called
an access point or AP.
Switches are fairly
dumb devices that just
have a lot of phone
jack like connectors,
a lot of ethernet connectors.
That once you plug in
all the ethernet cables,
the devices can all inter-communicate
with minimal amount of security.
And from there, the switch is connected
to probably one of Harvard's routers.
What is a router?
Guess even if you've
never heard the term.
A router routes information.
Yeah.
It really is that.
So you can think of
the internet as being
speckled with a whole bunch of routers
represented by those dots there.
And there are edges between
these dots or these nodes.
And what's interesting
about the internet
is that data doesn't necessarily
travel one predictable path or even
one same path on subsequent requests.
It's sort of this mesh network, whereby
each of those nodes is a router,
each of those dots is a router.
Each of the edges is just
a point of connectivity,
wired typically or wireless.
And so data can travel from point
A to point B by getting relayed
by all of these different routers.
And so when a router receives
a packet like this one here,
it looks at the to address and sees,
oh, this is destined for 1.2.3.4.
I know where that server is.
It's that way.
And so the router routes
the packet this way.
The next router in
turn might look at this
and be like, oh, I know
where this machine is.
It's that way.
And so it might hand this
off to the next router.
And by nature of how the
internet is configured,
typically it requires a max of 30 or so
hops, hand-offs, to get from one point
A to one point B around
the entire world.
And typically it's far fewer than that.
And it is the routers that decide how
to get the data with high probability
closer and closer and closer.
Not necessarily geographically.
Sometimes it's faster to
take a different direction.
Sometimes it's less expensive
to take a different direction.
But eventually the data actually
makes its way from point A to point B.
Indeed, you can see here
the IP address of a router.
Which of the routers in this
story is this IP address?
10.254.16.1.
And notice the similarity.
My IP address is almost the
same, but ends with 128.
Router IP addresses often, by human
convention, end with the number .1.
So you know that they're
on the same network.
Where is this router?
Whose router is this?
Or where in the story
is it would you think?
Harvard, yeah.
It's probably quite
proximal to this building.
Maybe it's in the basement.
Maybe it's around the corner.
It's one of Harvard's
routers presumably.
And in turn, that has some kind of
connectivity to these other routers
as well.
Typically these edges, these left right
decisions are dynamically configured.
So that if you unplug a router-- which
wouldn't typically happen but could
happen-- or if one router gets
congested, special protocols, software
that these routers are
running will dynamically
figure out which is the better or
newer or correct way to send the data.
And so it's all very
adaptive without humans
necessarily having to get involved.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Totally depends.
And it's different people along the way.
So Harvard, of course, owns
it's one or more routers.
I, in my home, might own
my tiny little router.
Which really can just
get data out of my home.
In the middle are lots of internet
service providers, big and small.
Level three is a very big one.
Verizon and Comcast have
their own networks as well.
There is yet other bigger fish.
Google has its own fiber
network and so forth--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Money.
They're peering points, so to speak.
So these larger internet
service providers typically
have financial agreements
between them that
govern how much they will pay
to send their data this way
or that way in order to get
data from one place to another.
They themselves are internally
incentivized to actually relay
the data to someone
if they actually want
to have customers whose data
can go from point A to point B.
And so sometimes the decisions to go
either to the left or to the right,
so to speak, might be made not so
much on technological decisions
but just on business decisions.
To whom do we have appearing connection?
And so even if you as a
business owner, for instance,
want to bring your-- run
your own servers, which
isn't as common an instinct these
days with cloud computing all
the rage-- more on that later-- if you
might have your own servers in a data
center in some warehouse out in
Western Massachusetts or New Jersey
or those kinds of places,
you would typically
decide for yourself who do you
want to pay to physically run
a cable into your servers, into
your part of the data center,
to establish exactly one
of those connections.
And that too would be a financial
decision and a reputation decision.
And not so much a technology one.
Yeah, David?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, a good question.
Why wouldn't you just have one
router and lots of switches
for the whole campus?
Part of it is distributed management.
So Harvard, for
instance, is a big place.
So let me oversimplify and say
each of the schools to some extent
might run its own local
network so that they
can have their own policies, their
own infrastructure, and so forth.
But they want to interconnect
to the rest of campus.
These days, Harvard
has been transitioning
to having more of a
monolithic infrastructure.
But there are still
side effects of this.
For instance, in a couple of
the offices that I spend time,
we can't actually-- we can have the
offices talk to one another certainly.
But we can't create
the illusion of what's
called a VLAN or virtual local area
network, whereby two separate buildings
appear to be the same network.
Simply because of legacy and
actual hardware limitations.
There's also performance.
For instance internal to campus,
there's only so much traffic.
But there's certainly a bottleneck
when you're leaving campus.
So you might have want to
have a separate route, a more
souped up router, that can actually
handle that outbound traffic.
Whereas you have smaller less
expensive routers internally.
And so it boils down to those kinds
of economic and logistical decisions.
Good question.
There's also security implications too.
A switch typically
operates technologically
at a certain level
that doesn't allow you
the same amount of control over what
comes in and out of your network.
Whereas a router is more of a
deliberate bottleneck that you have more
control over.
But the line is blurred
to some extent these days
between routers and
switches and their features.
As an aside.
This is a more arcane detail.
But does anyone-- has anyone
probably seen subnet mask before?
Someone know what subnet mask before is?
We don't have to get too
far into the weeds here.
But that is simply a number
that allows the local computer--
my Mac in this case-- to decide
when it is sending data from point A
to some other point B, if that other
computer is on the same local network
or if it's elsewhere on the internet.
And so essentially this
subnet mask, 255.255.240.0,
represents a pattern of ones and zeros.
It uses that patterns of ones
and zeros to determine, hm,
I am trying to request or send
information to this other server.
If that pattern of one
and zeros tells my Mac
that, ooh, that other computer is
on the local network, what's nice
is my computer will use a different
approach, a different protocol,
ethernet specifically, to
actually get the data from point A
to point B. It will never go
out on the public internet.
By contrast, if that
number reveals, oh, this
is actually a computer
that's far away, that's
how the computer decides to send
it not to the local network, LAN,
but to the next router
instead, to that IP.
So it all boils down to what
do you write on the envelope?
The local address or the
router's address instead.
So let's see if we can't see this.
Let me try to pull up.
Give me just one moment to see
if I can get into a server here
that will let us do this.
Nope, that won't do it.
That doesn't work.
Give me one moment.
Come on.
All right, let's do this.
All right.
Let's see if this works.
And then I'll explain
what we're doing here.
Whoops.
Transfer out.
All right.
Let's see if this gives me what I want.
Turn this around.
OK, this works.
OK.
So let's go ahead and
try this as follows.
-q 1.
OK, perfect.
MIT is seven hops away.
What did I just do?
So this is a command line program,
a text-based program on my Mac--
though an equivalent exists for PCs as
well-- and I ran traceroutes query one.
So just give me, send one request
at a time, to www.MIT.edu.
Because I am technically
interested in how data gets from
point A here at my laptop to
point B at MIT down the road.
And it turns out that
as we saw a moment ago,
the first hop that my data takes in
order to talk to MIT's web server
is to that address.
Which is the IP of what again?
Yeah, the router that my Mac
was preconfigured to use.
I don't recognize hop two.
It's just some other IP address.
But I do know it's also private.
It turns out that any IP address
that starts with the number 10
is a private IP address.
So you know it's being administered
locally by Harvard or by a family
member or someone in your company.
And if you're curious, this
is an inexhaustive list.
But anything ending in 10 dot something,
anything ending in-- starting with
172.16.something, anything
starting with 192.168.something.
So indeed if you go home
tonight or this coming week
and try to find your own Mac or PC's
IP address at home, or even at work,
perhaps, odds are it starts
with one of these values.
These are private IPs that
are, by human decision years
ago, never to appear
on the public internet.
They're meant to be used in homes and
businesses and campuses and the like.
So I know that one and two
are somewhere here on campus
because they have private IP addresses.
But then step 3 and 4 get
interesting because they have
what are called host names.
Semi-human friendly names that look
like domain names, and indeed they are.
And I know it's Harvard for sure.
But I don't know really
know where this is.
I do see its IP address.
This is a public IP
address at this point.
And I only know from convention,
coregw means core gateway.
Gateway as a synonym for router.
So this is like a core
router at Harvard.
So it's a really important router at
Harvard is as much as I can glean.
And what's interesting is that it
took three milliseconds for my data
to reach that router.
It took 1.75 for it to
reach the second router.
And two milliseconds to
reach the first router.
And what strikes you
about these three values?
Especially since I read
them in reverse order.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
They're not all the same.
So there's a lot of
variability or non-determinism
when it comes to sending
data on the internet.
The routers might be slightly
more busy at some times or other.
And by busy I mean maybe
more people are sending data.
And so it takes a moment
for the router to figure out
all of the different
decisions it has to make.
And that slows down my data
or someone else's data.
These are all pretty close.
They're all essentially
two, three milliseconds.
So it's still pretty fast.
But that variability is to be expected.
And these are not cumulative.
What this program is doing is it's
kind of putting its toe in the water
a little deeper and deeper each time.
How fast can I get to the first hop?
Then to the second hop?
Than to the third hop?
So it's progressively going.
They're not additive times.
Step four is another router that I just
know from convention is Border Gateway.
So this is probably another router
that Harvard owns that's on the border.
So figuratively speaking, the
edge, or maybe literally speaking,
the edge of campus.
Then it looks like Harvard's
internet service provider is Quest,
which is a really big ISP as well.
Like level 3 and others,
to your question earlier.
So Quest would be one of our
peers to whom we connect.
It looks like they have at least
two routers that are curiously
named the same in the same address.
I do not know why that is happening.
That seems to be a quirk
or a bug of some sort.
And then curiously, it
looks like MIT's website
has been outsourced to a company
that you might know of called Akamai.
They, among other things, are
a CDN content delivery network.
Which just means they run servers for
people to store their static files on.
So that MIT doesn't have to run its own
web servers, its own physical machines.
They just pay Akamai some number
of dollars per month or per year
to store it for them.
I have no idea what this number means.
It's probably just a
unique random identifier.
And this is apparently where
people deploy stuff too.
So that's all we know.
But it took 7 milliseconds to get to
MIT, as opposed to a good 15-20 minutes
by car or by [? T ?]
or by bike from here.
All right, so let's try another.
Trace route to Stanford.edu
and let's see what changes.
Same initial path, but now
step 5 is a little different.
The stars generally mean that
the router, for whatever reason
of misconfiguration or
deliberate security,
is just not responding to
the queries I'm sending.
So it's sort of anonymous.
Unfortunately, there
aren't many named router
as it seems between us and Stanford.edu.
And there's a lot of
anonymity between us and them.
So it started off somewhat
interesting, and now is
devolving into not very interesting.
Let's try someone else.
UCBerkeley.ed--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, we'll get there.
Berkeley.edu.
This one's juicier.
OK.
So what do we see here?
So here's-- this was new.
Nox, this is the northern crossroads.
This is a really big peering point
where lots of different internet service
providers interconnect in the Northeast.
Northern crossroads--
it looks like internet2,
the internet2 is a network
used primarily by universities
to be super fast, to
allow them to share data
and information in silly little
tests like this more effectively.
It looks like, curiously,
that step eight and nine
are kind of showing their
hand as to where they are.
Notice what changes between
step seven and eight What's
striking about these two routers?
What's different?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm sorry?
The time really jumps, right, from
seven milliseconds-- previous to that
was four and two, two, two milliseconds.
Now it's 50 milliseconds.
Where might step eight be?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
It's not a private versus public.
In fact, pretty much
everything right now
is public, by nature
of it being routers.
Right now everything you're
seeing is inside this internet.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Distance, yeah.
And it turns out that you can
sometimes infer from the host name,
just because of human
conventions for naming things
that step eight, that router, is
probably physically in Houston,
I'm guessing?
Texas.
So it's a good distance away from
wherever step seven actually was.
I'm not sure where it is
but probably the Northeast.
Meanwhile, step 10 is even
farther from step nine,
I'm guessing, because
of another jump in time.
Where might step 10 be?
LAX?
For whatever reason,
system administrators
have historically liked
naming routers after airports.
So this is probably in LA.
This one here, svl.
Still LAX.
I don't know what that is,
so I'll go with the LAX.
And then finally,
we've reached Berkeley.
And then for some reason, it's
just not responding further.
So it takes about 90 milliseconds
to send data to Berkeley.
Or about 5 or 6 hours to fly to Berkeley
to put things into sort of human terms.
And indeed, I think-- someone
suggested something abroad.
If we do like CNN.co.jp, the
Japanese version of CNN's website,
let's see if it cooperates here.
So again, we seem to have
taken the same direction.
A little anonymity there.
And then some really
interesting stuff going on
in step seven, eight, nine, and 10.
Massive jump here.
What might explain the striking increase
in time between hops nine and 10?
Pacific what?
Yeah, so the Pacific Ocean.
So indeed, there's huge
trans-Atlantic cables.
And trans-Pacific cables.
And just generally, oceanic cables that
carry a huge amount of internet traffic
that really big ships just slowly drag
and leave at the bottom of the ocean.
And indeed, it might take
100 additional milliseconds
to go from maybe California, can't
really tell from the names here
alone, to the coast of
Japan so many miles away.
So you can get a sense
there of distance as well.
And meanwhile, let's see
if we do-- one last one,
let's do like Yale.edu which is still
on this coast, and see what we get.
Here too we're going
to get similar results.
So nine or so milliseconds alone.
So this puts into more real
terms what's actually going on.
And a system administrator,
if he or she is
trying to diagnose some
issue with a network,
this is actually a real tool
that real people might actually
use to figure out where
is the data flowing.
Is one of the millisecond
counts way bigger than others,
is it anomalously large?
That might mean that one
router is malfunctioning
or it's just completely congested.
And so this is just one
such diagnostic tool.
But another one that's
useful to play with is this.
I proposed earlier that
people like Google.com
not have one IP address
publicly identifying them.
And indeed, if we hit
Google.com, in this case--
let's see if I'm about
to prove my point or not.
Nope.
OK.
Google has just one IP address.
Which is 172.217.0.46, which
is a little misleading.
But let's see what happens.
htp:// and that IP address.
And indeed, it brings
me to Google's website.
So if Google has this one IP address--
which does not demonstrate the point
I was hoping to make-- why
do they not just advertise
their URL as http://172.217.0.46?
Right, it's not meaningful.
I can't even read it,
let alone memorize it.
But this is kind of an interesting
upgrade from yesteryear.
Right?
Back in the day, some of us
might remember 1-800-COLLECT.
800 Which to this day, I don't
know what number that is.
But I know the mnemonic allowed
me to remember how to dial it,
so long as there's a mapping on the
phone pad to letters in this case.
And this is what DNS is for
the internet, essentially.
But it's automatic.
DNS is domain name system.
Which is to say that there are
special servers in the world whose
purpose in life is to translate numeric
addresses to fully qualified domain
names.
Host names like
Google.com and vice versa.
So we humans only have to remember,
and even our computers initially only
have to write the domain
name that the human provided.
And some other server, a
DNS server, will actually
do the automatic conversion.
And actually write at the end
of the day the numeric address
on the so-called virtual envelope.
But where-- David?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: You would hope so.
Not in this case, though.
So DNS also is a distributed system.
And it's a hierarchical system.
Which means there's lots
of caching that happens.
So it would be-- in
the extreme scenario,
suppose there is just one DNS
server in the world that knows
about all IP addresses and all names.
What's the downside of
that design intuitively?
If it goes down, gets jammed,
can't handle all of the traffic.
So that just feels like bad design,
whether or not you're an engineer.
So the DNS system has multiple servers.
But it doesn't just have duplicative
server, it has a hierarchical system.
So that there are some servers,
typically by convention, at least 13
root servers, whose purpose in life
isn't to know all of the answers,
but to know who has the answers.
And the root servers might know
who would know the answers for all
of the .com's, for all of the .gov's,
for all of the .jp's, and so forth.
Meanwhile, there is-- if
you think of a family tree.
If the root servers
are up here, you have
a second tier of servers
whose purpose in life
is to know those actual answers.
Or if they don't, to
know whom to ask in turn.
And that goes all the
way down to my laptop.
For efficiency purposes, when my
Mac first requests Google.com,
it obviously does not
know the IP address.
Because Apple did not ship this in every
Mac with the IP address of Google.com,
especially since it might change day to
day or week to week or a year to year.
But Harvard does have a DNS server.
But Harvard doesn't know the answers
to all IP addresses and host names
in the world.
But Harvard has it so its own internet
service provider that it could ask.
And maybe that internet service provider
has a bigger internet service provider.
And if that person doesn't
know, then at least
the root servers can help us
figure out who would actually know.
But along the way, once my Mac gets
that answer back the first time,
by convention, Mac OS and Windows
are going to remember or cache
the answer locally.
And why would they do that?
So you don't have to ask it again.
Which is good for efficiency.
And frankly, even browsers do this too.
Like Chrome and Internet
Explorer might actually
remember that information locally
along with other information as well.
So there's lots of layers
of caching for efficiency.
Of course, a side effect of this, if
you put back on the engineering hat,
what could go wrong if you're
caching information, especially
at multiple layers?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it makes it
really genuinely hard for Google
to change its IP.
Because if they change it,
well, when do they change it?
Well, if they change
it right now, my laptop
might remember the old IP address
for multiple minutes, hours, days.
It depends on how it was
configured or misconfigured.
So what does Google then do?
Well, maybe they could
do it late at night.
Unfortunately, Google
is a global company
and there is every possible time zone.
So just doing it at night
really has no meaning.
So that's not a solution.
They could run two servers in parallel.
Or at least two servers in parallel.
One with the old IP,
one with the new IP.
That gets us by.
But then we're getting new data on
both servers which probably isn't good
if we're trying to move to
some new server with an IP.
So this is actually a massive,
massive challenge these days.
And one of the ways that companies
like Google avoid this is one,
they only have one IP address.
And they use it as sort of the entry
point to the entire infrastructure.
So that hopefully, Google never has
to change this IP address, certainly
not frequently.
But they can change any number of
servers that are behind that IP address
so to speak.
So indeed, it is the case--
and we'll talk more about this
after lunch-- that there's a technology
called load balancing, whereby
even though my white lie earlier was
that every computer on the internet
has an IP address, that
doesn't necessarily
mean that's the IP address to
whom we speak when we send data.
There might be many other computers
behind a device that has that IP
address for purposes of balancing load.
But we'll come back to that again
when talking about cloud computing.
But not all companies do it that way.
If we look at Yahoo.com, Yahoo! it
would seem has three IP addresses.
This is a more obvious design.
They have at least three servers.
And frankly, they probably
have thousands of servers.
But these are the three ones they
expose publicly in terms of IPs.
And I just ran the same command again.
What did you notice is different?
The order changed.
And again, the order
is, again, different.
So it seems-- I'm just gleaning
this from running the command again
and again.
It's the same three IPs
but they're changing order.
It would seem that Yahoo uses round
robin load balancing-- more on this
in a bit-- whereby they give all
users the same three IP addresses,
but they change the order so
that my computer by default
uses just the first.
And this way, they put a
third of their users here,
a third of their users here,
a third of the users here.
Just probabilistically, based
on returning with 33% odds
a different one at the
top of the list each time.
All right.
So what actually happens?
Well, let's do this.
Suppose now, to make this more
clear as to what's going on here,
the internet as you may have heard
is filled with pictures of cats.
So suppose that one of you
in back, let's say Sean,
has requested a picture of a cat.
And I am the server, imgur.com
or Flickr or whatever.
And I am going to send
in this picture of a cat.
Unfortunately, it's
a pretty big picture.
It's a couple megabytes.
And that's not great for
everyone else in the room you
might want to be sending data to
each other or to Sean or from Sean
at the same time.
And so it turns out that what
IP does-- which doesn't just
describe IP addresses.
IP stands for itself, internet protocol.
And it works in conjunction
with another protocol called
TCP, transmission control protocol.
These are essentially conventions that
govern how the data gets from point A
to point B.
And a way to think of a protocol
is if I can come over here--
what's a human protocol?
Hello, my name is David.
[? Shavan ?]?
So this is a protocol, right?
Like I say hello, I extend my hand.
[? Shavan ?] knew sort of intuitively
to extend his hand, if awkwardly, to
stick my hand in the middle of class.
And then our transaction was complete.
Similarly does IP and CCP
govern just how computers speak.
They follow an initial kind of
hello, a subsequent kind of goodbye.
And it's just sort of preprogrammed
conventions that they adhere to.
And one of the features, meanwhile,
of these protocols, IP in particular,
is the ability to fragment things.
Because now, even
though in the real world
I've kind of ruined this
picture, in the digital world
I've just broken it up into four chunks.
A quarter of the bits are
here, a quarter of the bits
are here, quarter here, quarter here.
And now, I can put each of these
chunks in its own virtual envelope.
Which depending on the context you might
call a packet typically, or datagram,
or segment, which have minor
differences semantically.
But it just means that some
kind of virtual envelope
that zeros and ones go in.
And then I have to make sure,
of course, to address these.
So I'm going to go ahead and say that
Sean's IP address will be the number 1.
1.
So I'm just writing To: 1, To: 1.
So every envelope now has this
on it, if Sean was the first one
to get an IP address in the room.
But I need a little
more information in case
he wants to acknowledge receipt of
this cat-- which is what information?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: The from address.
So I'll be the second
computer in the world.
So I'm going to put From: 2,
From: 2, From: 2, and From: 2.
And then lastly, you might have
noticed this, I held this up.
What had I also written on the
envelope sort of preemptively.
Yeah, the order, the number.
So 1/4, 2/4, 3/4.
Why did I do that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: So he knows
how to put them back together.
One, two, three, four.
And also, I had a denominator
there for a reason.
So that he knows what?
When to stop.
It's not just that it's an infinite
string of pieces of cats like a puzzle
where you don't know where the edge is.
Now he knows where the edges.
And now much like we saw with some
of the data, that the data took
variable length paths,
which might have meant
taking different routes some times.
And much like there's multiple
interconnections, all of this data
is going to leave my hands
through the same router.
[? Shavan ?] is my default router.
But now if you could
presumptuously pass them,
but not necessarily the
same direction, the effect
here is to have a room full
of routers, each of whom
roughly knows where Sean is.
But is making perhaps
independent decisions.
Routing around blockages.
If some classmate's
not paying attention,
that might be the router is congested.
And so you pass it to
someone else instead.
Two of the packets have
gotten there quite quickly.
One is kind of stuck all over here.
And let me if I can steal this one
as though something went wrong.
And if, Sean, you'd like to reassemble
the cat and draw some conclusion.
Unfortunately, there's a problem.
I deliberately dropped or
let a packet be dropped.
And that happens.
I mean, much like the physical
this happening, routers will
by design drop packets.
Especially if they were overloaded.
Now I was sort of maliciously--
I took it away from David here.
But just as soon, I still
dropped it on the floor.
So what's your conclusion, Sean?
What are you missing?
AUDIENCE: I'm missing the
bottom right half. [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So it's corrupted or lost.
So it was probably, if I numbered them
right, four out of four or something
like that.
And so TCP is this protocol that
works in conjunction with IP.
Whereas IP is responsible for just
fragmenting things ultimately for size
and also addressing things, TCP, among
its features, is to guarantee delivery.
And it does it by way of
something called sequence numbers,
like my one, two, three,
four, and so forth.
It doesn't quite do it in the same way.
But it is a numbering scheme
from which Sean and people like
him can infer what packet is missing.
He is going to now send a response
back that he was missing for.
And TCP is a protocol that
allows me to, uh-oh, let me
go ahead and resend
him-- not everything,
because that could just lead
to the same cyclical problem--
but let me just send
him the missing piece.
And hopefully, with high probability,
it will get through this time.
Now, even though I've lost the piece of
the cat, we're talking zeros and ones.
So at the end of the day,
it's just duplicating data.
So there's infinite supply
of copies I can make.
And so hopefully this will
now get to Sean as well.
But this seems a given.
Like why is that a feature to
guarantee delivery on the internet?
Well, it turns out there is another
protocol that's sometimes used
called UDP, universal datagram protocol.
Did I remember my acronym right?
User datagram protocol, which
does not guarantee delivery.
Why in the world might
you want to use IP and UDP
when implementing some application
for your business or for fun?
As opposed to TCP IP, which
is the more commonly paired.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Speed, why?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
It's one fewer decision to make.
So if Sean doesn't even have to
think about what's missing, great.
Less work.
Less communicating with me.
Less resending by me.
That surely must take less time.
Good.
That--
AUDIENCE: Anonymity?
DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
DAVID J. MALAN: Anonymity.
Oh, so that's an interesting one.
A key ingredient or assumption of
Sean's ability to re-request packets
is that he has to know
from where it came.
Now in this case, it's
not quite applicable
because he presumably
asked me for the CAD.
So we already showed his
hand as to who he is.
But that would be true
in other scenarios
where you might want to send
information, maybe maliciously,
like spam or whatever without
it being traced back to you.
You don't want to resend.
If the recipient doesn't
get your spam, eh, so be it.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It could be.
But any of these could be peer to peer.
Just depends on how you use them.
Yeah, Sean?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: The sender doesn't--
and why might I not want a response?
AUDIENCE: Because it's
[INAUDIBLE] so many devices
out there, and [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
I mean if Sean had to acknowledge each
of the packets, that seems expensive.
It's doubling the amount
of traffic coming to me,
so that might be undesirable.
And what kinds of
applications would actually
be a feature not to waste time
retransmitting data if it's lost?
Instead just blowing ahead
and forgetting about it.
AUDIENCE: Video transmission?
DAVID J. MALAN: Video, why video.
AUDIENCE: Like if you're
Netflix gives out [INAUDIBLE]
back and watch what's already passed.
You just want to pick up and go.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
Although I would push back slightly.
I feel like Netflix users would
be annoyed if they're just
skipping parts of the show or movie.
But I can-- I would propose
tweaking your answer
to be a specialized use of video.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, [INAUDIBLE]-- I was
going to say, if it gets pixel-y,
I don't want to rewatch them.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, that's fair.
AUDIENCE: I just want to move on.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so that's fair.
But that would be, I
think, a different feature.
More quality of service.
Netflix and other companies, YouTube
have decided that users probably
would rather the screen
suddenly get pixillated,
but the audio still go through and
the video still be discernible.
Even if it's not as
good of an experience.
As opposed to buffering,
buffering, which is annoying.
But when might you-- but
it would be annoying,
I think, if all of a sudden
at the end of the reveal.
Like Sherlock is about
to discover the case
and you just skip it
because you lost those bits.
Minorly annoying.
But when is that less annoying?
What types of video?
AUDIENCE: Live stream [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Live.
Yeah.
So like baseball games,
sporting events, concerts.
Anything where the user, just
by nature of the experience,
would probably prefer
to be in real time,
even if it means an inferior experience
than having a great experience that's
buffered.
Especially if you're-- it's a little
awkward if you and your friends are
sort of rooting for your team to win
when your team won 10 minutes ago
because of buffering.
It kind of takes you out of reality.
So there might be a conscious decisions.
And not even just video-- not
video for like sports and events.
But what about video conferencing?
Right?
Then it's really problematic
if you're talking to someone,
but their remarks were uttered
seconds or minutes ago.
Really you want to just kind of blow
through it and rely on the humans
to retransmit their own voice
again, as opposed to resending
the bits that might have gotten lost.
All right.
So if we have these
ingredients, where the heck
did all this information come from?
Like all of you this morning, if you'd
never used Harvard's network before,
opened your laptop.
Went to Harvard University or Harvard
guest or whatnot, typed in a password.
But none of you typed in a DNS address,
none of you typed in a router address,
none of you certainly
typed in a subnet mask
or any of the things we've
been assuming we have.
So where does that come from?
Well it turns out there is
one other protocol that's
super popular and helpful
these days called DHCP.
And you might have
glimpsed this on my screen.
How is my Mac configured for IPv4?
Apparently using DHCP.
And this just means it's a protocol,
dynamic host configuration protocol,
that all Macs and PCs speak these days.
And its purpose in life is
to automatically configure
your Mac and PC.
Some of you might have had
internet service years ago
where the technician would come out.
He or she would have a sheet of paper.
And he or she or you would
have to manually type
in your IP address, your router
address, your subnet mask.
Even if you don't remember
it all these years later.
That was before there was DHCP.
Or at least supported by
the ISP and your computer.
But with DHCP, you open up your
laptop, you choose the Wi-Fi network.
And your computer essentially
says the equivalent
of hello, what IP address
should I use, what DNS server
should I use, what router should I use?
And Harvard, somewhere on
campus, has a DHCP server that
just responds with that information.
How does it know what to use?
Well, it turns out that Macs and PCs
have, confusingly, a MAC address.
Which does not mean Macintosh,
it means media access control.
Which is this hexadecimal address, where
hexadecimal is a 16-digit alphabet.
Binary is two, 0 and 1.
Decimal is 10, 0-9.
Hexadecimal is 0-F, where you count
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9--
can't say 10 because that's two digits.
So 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
a, b, c, d, e, f is the convention.
So this is hexadecimal.
But that's just a really big number
expressed with some letters and digits.
That is how Harvard
knows that you are you.
So even if you're cleverly,
like while here for the weekend
or here on campus in general, sort of
using incognito mode or private mode
in your browser,
thinking, ooh, I'm being
all incognito, like Harvard knows
who you are the entirety of the time.
Because if you registered your
computer on Harvard's network, one
of the pieces of information they
glean, besides your name and email
or password or whatever, is
your computer's MAC address.
Otherwise known as a hardware
address or ethernet address.
That is ultimately tied to you.
So there really is no anonymity on a
place like campus or in a business.
Because even that lowest
level detail is there.
And even though we haven't
discussed the MAC address,
it turns out we've
been over-simplifying.
Inside of each of these envelopes, much
like those old school Russian dolls,
there isn't just a cat.
The cat is actually
inside this envelope.
And this envelope is
And each of those envelopes has
slightly different information.
The outermost one might have
the IP address, to and from.
But the innermost one
might have a MAC address,
depending on where it is in the story.
Yeah, Avi.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: An IP address
is used to get your data
from one point to another
on a WAN, wide area network,
or for all intents and
purposes, the internet.
A MAC address is used to route
your data on a local network.
So in this room or in this
building, behind a router.
As soon as you involve
a router, you need IP.
If you don't have a router or need a
router, you can rely on a MAC address.
And so when I alluded
to subnet mask earlier,
it's the subnet mask that decides
should I address this packet using
the recipient's MAC address?
Or the router's MAC address?
Inside or outside?
Internal or external?
AUDIENCE: DNS?
DAVID J. MALAN: Felicia.
I'm sorry?
AUDIENCE: DNS?
DAVID J. MALAN: DNS
is domain name system.
That's the device that translates
IP addresses to host names and back.
So that is why I, the human, can
type Google.com and hit Enter.
My computer is going to quickly and
transparently ask the local DNS server,
what's the IP address for Google.com?
OK.
Let me write that on the
envelope instead of the words.
Because routers understand IP
addresses, not domain names.
David?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
to your MAC address?
DAVID J. MALAN: They would not, no.
So the outside world
does not see-- let me
make sure I'm not misspeaking--
they do not see MAC addresses.
Because the Mac address gets rewritten.
With every hop, it would be used
from router to router, for instance.
But the recipient would not see it.
And so I misspoke when I said--
when I was describing the envelope
inside of an envelope, it isn't
necessarily your MAC address
that's in there the whole time.
It's actually the MAC
address of the next hop.
The next router, router, router.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] right? [INAUDIBLE]
somewhere [INAUDIBLE] [INAUDIBLE]
probably they are doing it because
[INAUDIBLE] anonymous, right?
You don't have to [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It's a good q-- the
MAC address typically wouldn't-- you
wouldn't get caught by
way of your MAC address.
Unless the police or the Harvard
people, the security people,
were monitoring the local network
looking for your laptop to appear.
So for instance, let's see, if the
FBI or whoever, NSA, were-- and let's
just suppose they are
these days-- monitoring
all the traffic in this
room, they would see inside
of my virtual envelopes, my MAC address.
And so if they know from Harvard
that David has this MAC address,
then the whole world-- then rather--
we-- actually it occurs to me,
this is David's MAC address apparently
I'm showing on the whole world
here-- though it doesn't matter for
the same reasons we just discussed--
you could identify a
user by their MAC address
if you knew who owned it in advance.
Harvard is figuring out your
MAC address because when
you register it, when you first logged
in, the local network was detecting it.
And associating that MAC
address with your identity.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] So how
do they do it? [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: How do they
get caught or not get caught?
AUDIENCE: How do they figure
out who is sending [? email? ?]
DAVID J. MALAN: You know, so you
have to make a mistake along the way.
Or you have to somehow associate
yourself with the addresses
that the watchers are seeing.
So your computer has at
least two unique addresses.
Your IP address, which
is publicly routable,
and your MAC address,
which is locally routable.
The moment any of you registered
your computer on the Wi-Fi network
earlier today or earlier
this year, you forever
associated your identity with that
MAC address or that IP address.
Now, Harvard knows that.
So Harvard could be subpoenaed
for that information.
Even if you're a bad guy who's
just bought a disposable iPad,
the way to avoid this
is you somehow have
to change your MAC
address, which is possible,
or spoof your IP address to match
that of someone else who is already
registered.
That is absolutely already possible.
But barring that, even if you do
that, all the bad guy has to do
is mess up just once.
If he or she visit some
website that is not encrypted--
that is the information's
not scrambled--
and they just log into their
email account or some service
once, if the NSA has been
logging all of that traffic,
they can just go back through
weeks or years worth of data.
And all you have to do is to have
screwed up once in order for them
to then rewind history and say oh, if
this was David at this point in time,
it must have been David
with high probability
in all previous points in time.
And that's the danger of something like
what the NSA was doing for some time.
They're not just looking
at moments in time.
If they're storing information
for a ridiculous amount of time,
all you have to do is
reveal yourself once.
And you can reconstruct
that entire history.
And that's what's especially frightening
about the storage of so much data.
So in short, it's really hard.
You have to be so careful.
And not just-- and
never screw up really.
Or never screw up and be noticed.
And in fact, there's-- I
forget what the case is.
I just read the other
night and might pull it up
for tomorrow's discussion of security.
There was a case where the bad
guys thought they were being clever
by not actually sending emails.
They were logging into
some shared email account.
They would compose a
draft email, not send it.
But then the other bad guy
would log into the same account,
look at the drafts email.
Because they were thinking presumably
it's not going out on the internet.
Which did narrow the scope of the
threat to their malicious behavior.
But even then, the server, whoever
it was, Yahoo or Facebook or whoever,
was surely logging who was
accessing that shared account.
So with corporate cooperation can
you reveal what's going on as well.
AUDIENCE: So maybe my next
question is so where [INAUDIBLE]
And how do they control [INAUDIBLE]
So where-- how do they control that?
And my last question is [INAUDIBLE].
But it would be [INAUDIBLE]
on the internet.
Right?
So if you've changed IP addresses to
your numbers, how is that being done?
Is there--
DAVID J. MALAN: There is an
Internet Assigned Numbers Authority,
which is a nonprofit entity
that's responsible for allocating
IP addresses throughout the world.
They typically sell or rent IP addresses
to bigger fish like internet service
providers.
Who in turn rent them effectively
to little people like us.
Our home or our smaller business
or smaller school or the like.
So there's a hierarchical
system for allocating them
in a way that ensures that
the same IP address is not
rented to multiple people.
In terms of where you sniff
traffic, you can certainly
sniff it in any of these points.
And that's what's so
frightening about sending data
on the internet from point A to
point B, were B is who knows where.
Because anyone with physical access
to any of these wires or any of these
physical machines could absolutely
be snooping on all of our data.
Our best defense is disinterest.
If no one really cares what we're
doing, that sort of our best protection.
But if you do have a threat or someone
is just fishing for information,
whether it's a government or a
company or a hacker or the like,
they can look at all of the unencrypted
traffic inside of this network.
Which is a lot of
unencrypted traffic today.
In terms of companies or
countries, they would typically,
especially in certain Asian countries
or Middle Eastern countries where
there are very tight restrictions
these days on internet connectivity,
they will generally have relatively
few-- or in the extreme case, only one
router that routes data from inside
the country to outside the country.
And so the great firewall
of China or restrictions
in Pakistan or other
countries might just
have relatively few devices that
are imposing those firewall rules,
preventing Facebook traffic from
coming in or going out, for instance.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] So how do
they control them? [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It's harder.
I mean, if you are
running-- well, if you've
built your own Facebook knockoff,
you have one or more IP addresses
associated with it.
So even if you're running those
within the boundaries of the country,
if you only have a finite
number of IP addresses,
the country could, if
they control DNS, simply
prevent resolution for
like ourFacebook.com
from actually being
converted to IP addresses.
So there are sort of choke points
that you could exercise control over.
Whether it's at the packet level
or at the system level like this.
In fact, there was a mistake at one
point where some country or company
accidentally brought
down much of the internet
abroad for a brief amount of time.
Just because of a
misconfiguration of DNS.
And because so many
people are reliant on DNS.
If this starts returning
bogus information or just
incorrect information, it
has this cascading effect
of breaking most anything.
So there's lots of different ways.
I mean, mostly what's happening
in recent years and months
with all these revelations is
people are just realizing how
insecure the network has always been.
These are not new threats.
These are just threats that
are being more publicized.
But lots more scary
stories tomorrow, as well.
All right.
So where did this come from?
DHCP.
So dynamic host configuration protocol.
So that's just something that our Mac
or PC is pre-configured to know about.
So what is that actually
let us do ultimately?
Is actually use the internet
without actually having
to manually configure our machine.
All right.
So let's toss a couple of
more items into alphabet soup.
Which is actually germane
to exactly that chat.
And some of you might use this
at work, even if you're not
quite sure what it's doing for you.
Who here uses a VPN for work?
OK.
So about a quarter of the folks here.
Why do you use it?
Or what does it do for you?
Grace?
AUDIENCE: Just to access
any of our secure data
or certain websites or
tools [INAUDIBLE] VPN.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, to access certain
websites or tools within the company.
[? Avi ?]?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: To remotely
access the local network,
back home or at your company.
Anyone else have disparate use cases?
This is generally the principle.
VPN is virtual private network.
And it allows you to by
running some software,
usually logging in with the username and
password that maybe get preconfigured,
to create the illusion that your
computer is not on Harvard's network,
for instance, but on your
own company's network.
And
So you will suddenly
have an IP address that
appears to be not only--
you have two IP addresses.
One that's at Harvard, and
often one is that your company
or at your home, wherever the
end point is for that VPN.
The upside of that is that
if your company or your home
or your campus' system administrators
have decided this financial software
or whatever is just too
sensitive to be on the internet,
we want people to be physically
or virtually on our network,
they can restrict access to that
piece of software or website
or whatever to only those people
who are on the network physically,
or virtually, as via VPN
in the latter scenario.
The upside of this is that you
have a secure connection encrypted.
All of the traffic to in
Grace's laptop, wherever
she is in the world and
her company, are encrypted.
So that even if a bad guy
sees zeros and ones flying by,
they're seemingly random.
And they're not information that
they could glean much detail from.
The VPN has another application.
Why do some people abroad in the
countries like we've been describing
or the scenarios use VPN?
What problem might it also solve?
AUDIENCE: For instance, China
where Facebook is blocked,
people use VPN to access Facebook.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's surprising how
many Harvard undergrads
seem to visit China and
posts on Facebook while
in China, which is blocked.
But the reality is that if you have
enough technical savvy and enough
access technologically, you could, in
theory, in China or any other country
use your laptop to establish a VPN
connection, a virtual private network
connection, to a place like
Harvard or your company.
Or you can even pay
third parties these days
to have a VPN connection
in any number of countries
to really bounce yourself
around the world.
And what happens then is that
China or whatever the country is
would know that you have an
internet connection between you
and the outside world.
But by nature of it being
encrypted, they can't see inside.
And so they therefore either by
conscious choice or disinterest
or oversight, allow you to
maintain that connection.
But the result is that all
of your Facebook traffic
doesn't go directly from you in
that country to Facebook.com.
It first goes through America or
wherever your VPN server actually
is or company actually is.
Then it goes to Facebook.
Then it goes back to your company.
Then it goes to you.
So just intuitively, what's
the downside of this approach
to circumventing those
kinds of protections?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: It's got to be
slower if you're adding distance.
And frankly, you're adding cryptography.
More on that tomorrow.
You're adding the
scrambling of information
which takes a non-zero amount of time.
Might slow things down.
But the upside, of course,
is that you can access,
theoretically, protected resources.
Now, there is no reason
the country or the company
couldn't prevent VPN connections,
or prevent VPN connections
to known places like Harvard.edu.
But assuming the cryptography,
the scrambling information
is correct and secure, they
at least can't see what's
inside of it if they do allow it.
So these are the kinds of trade-offs.
But VPN services seems to be
very much in vogue these days.
And people do not so much
for issues of-- well, still
for issues of circumvention.
VPNs are very popular among Netflix
subscribers and Hulu subscribers.
Why?
AUDIENCE: Access location
specific streams?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
location specific streams.
So like certain shows only
air in the UK initially.
And so you might want-- like Downtown
Abbey, if you were really into that,
and you want to get access before PBS in
the US has it, you can VPN into the UK
and watch it on whatever the network--
the BBC's channels there, perhaps.
Netflix was in the press recently
because they've been clamping down
on their own customers' use of VPNs.
Because if you're traveling abroad--
even if you're a legitimate Netflix
subscriber but you travel abroad,
and you go to Netflix.com,
log in with your American
account, you might still not
be able to access the resources.
Because of whatever partner
or licensing arrangements
they've made with the big
film studios and TV studios,
they just won't stream it to you.
Unless you pretend to be in America,
as you could with a VPN service.
But there are certain VPN services that
have gotten super popular, it seems.
So Netflix simply blacklists
their IP addresses.
So that even that doesn't work.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Sure.
So Tor is an interesting thing.
This is the-- Tor Onion
Router, so to speak,
which is an anonymous technology.
This essentially allows you
and your laptop or desktop
to create essentially a
multi-hub VPN connection.
Where you connect to someone else,
he or she connects to someone else,
he or she connects to someone else.
So you have these several
layers of indirection
that aren't at the router level.
They're just at individual
laptops or desktops.
But the result is that you have
plausible deniability in some way.
Whereby if you are requesting some
websites that's way over here,
but your traffic appears
to, not unlike the movies
have come from here to here to here to
here to here to here to here to here,
the resulting website isn't
going to know who you are.
They're going to know you
only as whoever the most
recent hop in that network was.
So that might seem to put them at a
disadvantage and you at an advantage.
But insofar as you're participating
in this anonymization network,
the same might be true when that person
wants to access something anonymously
that your request might appear
to be coming from your laptop.
The catch, though, is that certainly
if all of the middlemen in the story
reveal their logs.
Like everyone in the story knows
to whom they've been connecting
and to whom they're connecting.
So you're really just making it
harder for like subpoenas to chip
away at this problem.
You'd have to subpoena this
machine, this machine, this machine,
this machine.
And if they're well
configured technologically,
they won't remember any of this
information by design anyway.
But it's not foolproof.
In fact, a few years ago
there was a bomb scare
at Harvard during, coincidentally, exam
period, which was actually traced back
to a student, I believe.
Even though he-- and this is
all publicly documented in
newspaper articles-- was using,
I believe, Tor at the time.
The problem, though, is
that-- and I'm only inferring,
I think, from the details-- if you're
the only Tor user, or one of few Tor
users on campus when a
bomb threat is called in,
you might appear to be anonymous.
But that protocol is still identifiable.
So you might not know,
or the authorities
might not know what those
few Tor users were doing.
But they certainly knew who
presumably to question first.
And so it only helps
in certain scenarios.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
The more, the better.
But even then-- Google up on
it, security of Tor networks.
The folks at the edges are
sometimes exposed nonetheless
because of issues like this.
So it's not something to sort of build
a business or super secure communication
on necessarily.
It helps, but nothing is foolproof.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: To what?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh.
So that's very different.
I know less about that one.
But let's come back to that one
tomorrow morning in more detail.
Less we go too far into security today.
Other questions?
All right.
So we have this whole
alphabet soup, all of which
together actually allow
us to do something.
So what is that something?
What is one of the most common things?
Let's conclude our look at internet
technologies at the one that most of us
are using so much these days,
which is web related stuff.
And in fact the one acronym we haven't
mentioned yet that you sort of see
or use all the time is http.
Hyper text transfer protocol.
Which is yet another sort of
handshake kind of protocol
that dictates how computers
interact with servers.
And what is http used for?
Well, typically in a
browser, back in the day,
you would type
http://www.google.com and hit Enter.
Nowadays most of us
probably don't type http.
We've sort of fallen out of that habit.
Most of us probably don't
even type www these days.
Why is that but none of us
seem to do that anymore?
DNS is true.
So long as Google.com has an IP
address and not just www.google.com,
it will just work.
And in fact, web servers
can forcibly redirect you.
If you visit Google.com,
they can send a response
that is not Google's home page.
It's an initial response that
says no, go here instead.
Your browser will then behind the
scenes request www.google.com,
thereby filling in the blanks for you.
Why do we humans rarely
if ever type http anymore?
AUDIENCE: Protocol?
DAVID J. MALAN: New protocol?
Not even.
This is more of a--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
DAVID J. MALAN: The
browser does it for you.
Right?
If you're using a browser--
even though browsers actually
can do a few different things,
typically, different protocols FTP,
http, and a few others
sometimes-- the reality
is 99 point whatever percent
of the time you're just
using them for http traffic.
So you want your browser to speak this
protocol, which we'll see in a moment.
And so it's just inferred.
And in fact, browsers even assume
that if you type in something dot com
and something dot com doesn't exist,
they will often presumptuously pre-pend
for you www.-- try that address just
in case the website's not configured
for you.
In fact, I still remember, it was an
amazing example for class discussions,
years ago http://harvard.edu
did not work.
Which was infuriating, because you'd
go to it and you'd hit a dead end.
Which sort of doesn't
reflect well, I think.
But it was an amazing opportunity to
discuss in class why it was broken.
And then at some point,
I must-- someone new
was hired at Harvard who similarly
thought this was ridiculous.
And within days it was fixed.
So unfortunately, it's
not a good story anymore.
But it is purely by human
convention that most websites still
start with www.
And in fact, it's why you see on
advertisements something advertised
as www.something.com, because
for a lot of users out there,
technophobes some of them
or less technical people,
it's a visual identifier
that this is a website.
Now these days, you might argue
that do you really need it?
Like what's another good visual
cue that when you see something
you should type it into a browser.
.com alone is pretty good.
But nowadays, this is a new problem
that will start to resurge again.
Most of us have seen .com and .edu
and probably .net and probably .org.
But there is bunches of
others like .travel--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Dot what?
.gl, .tv, .io.
And to make a bad problem worse, if
you go to a website now, Registrar--
more on this in a moment-- there
are an atrocious number of generic
TLD's as they're called-- and this
is a recent change in the past year
or so where the world just got really
messy-- OK. .guru, .clothing, .singles,
.holdings, .ventures, .equipment,
.plumbing, .cam-- I mean, it's just--
I'm embarrassed to say them all.
They're just so innumerable now.
So gone are the days-- now you
just have to look for a period.
And when you see a period or a dot, like
type it into a browser it would seem.
So there's kind of
this interesting issue
now, whereby much like we benefited
with the phone numbers for years.
Like if you saw 800 dash
something, dash something,
you just knew intuitively
it was a phone number.
No one had to tell you to
call this number necessarily.
And we've had that same
tendency for first with http.
Then we just www.
Then with .com.
And now there's perhaps a regression
in so far as I know lots of people--
and even I wouldn't
necessarily know that if they
see something dot
something that it's not
just some trendy way of
marketing your sort of syntax
as opposed to it being
an actual domain name.
So it'll be interesting
to see what happens now.
But this is to say that websites
ultimately have domain names.
And they're accessed by
way of this protocol, http.
And let's see what it looks like.
It turns out that if I go
to google.com, I of course
see a page that looks a
little something like this.
Most browsers have a feature
somewhere like under Chrome,
it's under Developer, View Source, where
you can actually see the underlying
code that composes the web page.
This isn't programming code per se.
This is mostly a language called
html and css, more on that
later this afternoon.
But this is the language in
which web pages are written.
It's scary looking here because Google
has compacted it as much as possible.
And it does a little more than a typical
website might in terms of features.
But this is what was inside
the virtual envelope.
So Sean got a cat.
But when I go to google.com, I get all
of this inside of my virtual envelopes.
And together, remarkably, all of
this implements just this simplicity.
But there's actually some programming
code in a language called JavaScript
there as well.
But notice, I can get
that same response.
I'm going to pretend
to be a browser here.
I'm going to run a program
called Telnet which
is an old school program, good for
diagnostics these days, to Google.com.
That's the server to
which I want to connect.
And specifically, I want
to connect to port 80.
It turns out that TCP which we discussed
earlier, which guarantees delivery,
it also, among its features assigns
numbers to different services.
So if I summarize a
couple of these, 80 is
for-- actually, we'll do it right here.
Http has the TCP port number called 80.
Https, which most folks
probably know means secure,
it's encrypted somehow-- more
on that tomorrow-- is 443.
Email, otherwise known as
simple mail transfer protocol,
is usually on port 25 or 487 or--
I'm getting this wrong-- 5-- 46--
I can't remember offhand.
Usually on 25.
And two other numbers.
400-something and 500-something.
But in short, I'm going to
use this Telnet program now
to connect to Google
server on that port.
So I'm not sending an email as
it might look like if I did this.
I'm instead pretending to be a browser.
And notice that I'm
connected to google.com.
I can now type textually, just for
demonstration's sake, the following.
GET / HTTP/1.1 from the
host www.google.com.
What I have just typed
is the digital equivalent
of my having extended my
hand to [? Shavan ?] earlier.
This is what's inside
my virtual envelope
when I request a page from Google.
When I hit Enter now, I get
back all of that messiness.
Which previously we saw
in Chrome, now I just
see in my little black and white window.
But that's all http is.
It has more commands
and more instructions
that the server understands.
But at its essence, all
you are saying is get me
a specific URL with version like
1.1 of the particular protocol.
And that's all that's happening there.
And if you're using https, all of
that goes and it comes back encrypted,
scrambled.
So what does that mean
at the end of the day?
At the end of the day,
this web page still
needs to get written
in another language.
And we'll come back to that later.
The other language is
going to be something
called htmp, HyperText Markup Language.
With something called CSS,
cascading style sheets.
Also some JavaScript.
More on that tomorrow.
And if I'm ever rattling off
acronyms just super fast,
it's because usually that doesn't
matter what they are, but how they work
or how they're relevant.
And html and CSS are
the actual languages
that implement underneath
the hood the web page.
So let's answer one final question.
Where did www.google.com come from?
Or if you're starting a business or if
you have some personal portfolio site
and you want to put
yourself on the internet
with your own domain
name, what do you do?
Does anyone want to offer
if you've done this before?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Register, OK.
So you go to an internet
registrar so to speak.
Registrar.
And there's dozens, if not
hundreds, of them these days.
And from them you buy a domain name.
Or you kind of rent the domain name.
Because by nature of how
the internet was set up,
we pay annually for these things.
From like $5 to maybe $200 depending on
which top level domain or TLD you want.
By TLD I mean .com or .org or .guru.
In fact, if we go back
to namecheap, which
is a popular, fairly
inexpensive website,
if I want to get computerscience.guru,
search, let's see if this is available.
It is not available,
someone already owns that.
Let's see what it is.
Nope, they're not
doing anything with it.
Oh and notice, maybe now
even Chrome's error messages
make a little more sense.
Computer science guru server's
DNS address could not be found.
So that means that my
computer tried to figure out
the IP address of
computerscience.guru, and it
seems the person might have
paid for this domain name
but not actually done step two.
Which is actually an amazing
segue to what step two should be.
Once you own the domain name,
what comes next if you've done it?
AUDIENCE: Link it to an IP address.
DAVID J. MALAN: You have to
link it to an IP address.
So you need some kind
of web host, which would
be the generic way of describing it.
And this is either your own server.
You could in theory run your
own server, get an IP address
or plug it into the
internet and so forth.
Most people don't do that these days.
They'll use a cloud service.
More on that after lunch time.
But you'll sign up for someone
like dreamhost.com or heroku.com
or Amazon Web Services or Microsoft
Azure or Google App Engine.
Or any number of third parties
who run servers and software
and give you storage space where
you can put all of your files,
all of your web content, and they
give you an IP address, or really
a shared IP address, maybe
with other sites using it.
And you actually put your content here.
And so there's two
steps, and both of these
involve some kind of
financial transaction
if you're indeed using someone
else's servers and software
to run your website.
And there's more steps in between.
Generally, it's documented and it
completely varies by whom you partner
with.
But we'll see later today what it looks
like to actually write code that you
might put on to step two servers.